- So our panelists, and I put 'em in alphabetical order.
Dr. Kathy Bakhit. - Hi, everyone.
- She is the Vice President
of Academic Affairs at Antelope Valley College,
and she has over over 30 years of education,
I'm sorry, 30 years of experience in education,
beginning from an ESL student to like, she got, you know,
personal insight, how it feels to go
through the entire system.
And now she's the VP of AA and at Will Valley College.
- Thank you. - Yay.
And she holds a doctorate in educational leadership
and a background in economics, facilitating efforts at ABC
to just allow us to do amazing work in AI.
Sorry, I've got a little asthma going.
Alright, then,
Chesa Caparas. - Hi, everyone.
- Hi.
- We didn't follow instructions.
- And she is a public speaker
and professor of English and ethics studies at De Anza,
where she teaches the impact of API learning community
and leads faculty development on AI and education.
She's a Fulbright Scholar, alumni, ambassador,
and has served as a California Learning Lab AI,
I'm gonna say this wrong.
AI first. Yes.
And which is a faculty innovator in residence.
And Dr. Sarah Harmon. Woo.
She is the OER and ZTC project manager
and an adjunct professor of linguistics at Cañada College.
It's the one with the little squiggly line over the N. Okay.
And of course you had to add that.
What is that called?
- Not Canada.
- What is that officially called?
- Tilded.
- That one. - Yeah.
- Okay. Over 25 years experience of teaching.
Been a leader in expanding zero and low cost burden free,
yeah, course materials, managing major ZTE grants,
authoring textbooks.
Amazing.
She explores the intersection of OER and AI.
And she's part of the new CCC,
Chancellor's Office AI change maker.
Woo.
And we have Dr. Michelle Fischthal,
and she's a Vice Chancellor of Institutional Innovation
and Effectiveness at San Diego Community College
in that district.
And serving nearly 80,000 students.
I know, right?
She leads these district planning, research
and technology and integration with a focus on AI
and extended reality.
This is cool. - It is.
- She has structured the district's multi-college
AI initiative and she co-leads the Equity AI Alliance
with San Diego State University, SDSU
and UC, San Diego, and serves on many boards.
Ooh, that's a lot of boards. Okay.
And she's known for her wonderful collaboration,
helping higher educators
and institutions thoughtfully embrace emerging technologies.
Round of applause for our board.
(people clapping)
All right, so,
these are our panelists.
So let's start with our first question. Is that cool?
- Sure. Go for it.
- And so in this one we're asking,
please share specific examples of
how your district area is supporting learning
and teaching with respect to AI.
- Who wants to go?
- Any order.
- You. - Me?
- I'm the going director.
- They say me.
So examples how our district is supporting learning
and teaching with respect to AI.
So my division has been in existence
for two and a half years.
It was very intentionally created
to have an executive on the chancellor's cabinet
around both emerging technology but also research
and planning, and strategic planning
as well as accreditation.
And so two months,
I started my job in February of 2023.
The division started in 2023 February,
just a few months after AI.
And the first thing that I did was put out a survey to see
where folks were in terms of emerging technology.
And obviously AI came up as something that we had
to address immediately.
So I'm going to skip two and a half, two years.
I'll talk about that hopefully a little bit later.
But in terms of supporting AI,
and you may have heard Alison Gurganus
at the end of yesterday, she and I worked together.
It's really been all about AI literacy.
I knew straight away that number one, we needed
to start with faculty.
And two, that I needed support of faculty to support faculty
in terms of AI literacy.
That as a vice chancellor going out
and doing AI literacy training would probably not go
over very well.
So we really started out trying to build an infrastructure
to support faculty
to ultimately support our students.
And we've done a lot of work since then,
but I'm going to leave it to
lots of work workshops.
We started out with lots of workshops.
We've migrated into creating spaces for faculty
to talk together with just implementing communities
of inquiry and practice discipline specific.
We recognized that that was an important space to go.
And then you heard in my bio this AI Equity Alliance
with San Diego State University in UC San Diego.
And that's part of the AI Challenge grant.
And that's very explicitly to also, there's a piece of that
that will bring in both microcredentials,
AI microcredentials for students as well as faculty
and staff, as well as what we're calling our innovation hub,
which is to bring faculty again together
to have conversations.
So we've been building for two and a half years now,
and it feels like we're finally getting some motion,
but it's all about what can we be doing
to support everyone in our institution
and how can we be leveraging resources to do that.
So I'll stop there and hand it to someone else.
- Oh, sure.
So I'm in the Foothill De Anza district,
so you've probably seen our name plastered
all over all this stuff.
So you know how on one level,
how the district is supporting AI work, is this better?
Is this better? Okay, cool.
And so maybe just to give a little bit of background,
we do a lot of AI professional development like,
but first at the college level
and then at the district level supported
by our Office of Professional Development.
But I wanna speak also from a personal note,
because one of the ways
that professional development is supported is I am fortunate
enough that I had a sabbatical, right?
And so for my sabbatical project,
I did the Fulbright research on disinformation
during a very contentious election season in
the Philippines, which as you can see probably relates to
some of the things we're experiencing in
the United States right now.
And as soon as I came back in 2022 ChatGPT dropped.
And so my whole sabbatical project was about AI literacy
and how do we use it to teach about how to, you know,
engage civically, how to spot disinformation.
And so that's sort of been some of the philosophy
behind the professional development.
And through leading those, I have been able to grow this,
I mean, or sorry, connect with this amazing network
of things that are happening both at De Anza
and Foothill, such as the Emerging Technologies Institute
and this AI learning community that is run at Foothill.
Because what I've really noticed is anytime
that we're talking about these emerging technologies,
we really have to center human relationships.
And that's part of like the title of this panel is
how do we get humans to talk to each other about the ways
that these technologies are impacting us.
So, you know, working with online ed office
and you know, seeing how it's impacting faculty
and talk to our classified professionals about
how is this really impacting your work?
I feel like that's sort of the important work
that the district and, you know, some of the areas
that I've mentioned have been leaning into.
- So, oh, that's not on done. My god. Now this, okay.
And my loud voice has to get toned down a little bit.
I realize.
Anyway, so to talk about being new in a position,
I literally have been the OER ZTC program manager for,
I think it's two weeks now.
- [Panelist] And three hours.
- Oh yeah. Three hours. Yes, you're right.
So, but it builds on the work that I've been doing
as a faculty member.
I was adjunct faculty of Spanish and linguistics at Cañada.
I dropped the Spanish because I'm focusing so much more now
on OER.
But I also was a faculty coordinator for all things OER
and I sat as the chair
of our district academic Senate Standing Committee
on Teaching and Learning.
That's a really long title.
So we usually just say District Teaching
and learning committee,
and that is through San Mateo District's Academic Senate.
And when all the ChatGPT love started,
we really focused on the 10 plus one
and the role of faculty in everything with respect
to guidance policy, how we teach, how we teach each other,
how we teach our students, how we work
with our colleagues at every office on campus.
So district teaching and learning started with
an AI guidance, that's a website
that has a list of best practices, connects directly
with the instructional designers at all three campuses.
So that's Skyline College, that's College of San Mateo
and Kenyatta College.
And then I lovingly turned all of this over to...
I forgot the other piece that is coming out,
that we start our first community of practice build on AI
that includes not just how to use these tools,
but also the ethics and digital literacy component.
And then I handed it all off to my colleague,
Dr. Jennifer House Owens, who is now the current chair
of district teaching and Learning.
So this is a collaborative effort.
It is faculty led, but it is a collaborative effort.
District teaching and learning is a primarily a faculty
group, but it also includes at least one instructional dean.
It always has other classified professionals in there,
especially instructional technologists, but others as well.
I believe this year they have a director of
disability resource center as part of
the membership, exactly to address so many of the things
that we'll end up talking about later.
And then it is also co-chaired
by our district's Vice Chancellor
of Educational Services and Planning.
So that ties in not just the three colleges at various
levels, but the district office as well.
- Cool. Hi again, everyone.
I'm Kathy Bakhit, Vice President Academic Affairs at
Antelope Valley College.
I have the privilege of working with Dr. Norma Jones.
And the way Norma and I connected illustrates
how I approach leadership on AI and other things.
And just in terms of my background,
my background is in economics.
And so having that background, I am naturally inclined
to stay in touch with industry trends and what's going on.
And so I was hired at Antelope Valley College.
It was August of '23.
And the first week when we had flex week,
I saw it was, again, it was the beginning
of the activities around AI.
I saw a webinar,
I don't know which organization was offering it.
I sent an email across campus to all faculty.
I am attending this webinar, join me if you're interested.
Lo and behold, about 10 people did.
And that is an organic way of engaging people
and building the coalition of the willing.
And so that organic at work group
started meeting and continuing to learn
and sharing their knowledge with their colleagues.
And so we have offered, they have, they,
and you know, I supported them, the college,
we have offered tens and tens of workshops on
the topic they have.
They're learning to how to produce videos,
how to support teaching and learning.
Quickly the conversation went into naturally cheating
and policies, distance education policy,
how to change our board policy to adapt for it,
the whole turn it in conversation.
Like what do we do about it?
Because we can't, especially for minoritized students,
we can't accuse them of cheating if we can't prove it.
And so if you do that, you are asking for trouble
because there's no evidence, there's no tool
that it can verify with high level of certainty
that a student has copied from AI.
You can suspect it, but you can't prove it.
And those are two different things.
Anyhow, so organic engagement
and me as, as the leader, also staying in the know.
I cannot have a conversation
and understand the faculty concerns
if I don't know what AI is
and what are the advantages, what are the opportunities,
and what are the risks too.
And so using the infrastructure of the college
and the shared governance,
we had presentations at dean's councils,
at chair's councils, during flex week,
and highlighting their work.
We had events celebrations awards
to thank their work group
and encouraged everyone to engage in the conversation.
Let's see here.
Supporting industry connection
and partnerships with the community.
So we are working with the Chamber of Commerce
and business organizations to develop curriculum
to support how do we encourage
or support the entrepreneurs in implementing AI
in their shops
because that will help them in terms of productivity.
Let's see here.
Travel obviously and allocating resources to it
and so much more.
I'm sure it'll come back to me.
But those are some of the, the, some of the ideas
around supporting and leading AI work.
- Cool. Thank you. May I ask a follow up?
- Sure.
- We have different roles, right?
Chancellor, VP of academic affairs,
coordinator level faculty,
and a leader in the AI space across this, you know,
a lot of humility happening.
Amazing people.
And this is the part where I say, okay,
in your different roles,
how would you like someone from administration,
someone from faculty, the roles that you're not in,
what are some of the things that you think would,
that you've seen that really work really well?
And I think we illustrated this where that we,
how I wanna try this, is it okay?
Right, and then we talked about like, I think we got what,
nine classes in? - Yep.
- Through our curriculum this week.
So I was like, oh, right.
So what are these things that you would see from your role
that has worked well across the different roles
that you occupy?
- I can get us started because-
- It's yours.
- I have this, oh, I will say
as a primarily faculty person,
especially when I lead AI professional development,
it has been so helpful when I just lead with,
it's okay if you are too burned out to do this right now.
I mean, we have to recognize, I know
that the toll has been great on like all levels,
administrators, et cetera.
But faculty, we are on the ground
with our students every day.
The visceral feeling of, you know,
even if I allow AI in my classroom, the visceral feeling
of like, ugh, a student like used it unethically again, like
that is something that, you know,
administrators might not understand
when they're creating policy.
Like what is it like to look a student in the face
and say, I don't know if I can accept this
because I'm not sure like where the thinking
or the writing happens
and it, I'm not saying that I ever fail those students.
I'm saying let's have a conversation.
But I feel like it's really important for, you know,
I would love administrators and leaders,
especially policy makers, to just know
what the experience is like when you're meeting with
like dozens, hundreds, you know, our classes are huge
so remember that too, of students.
And it's not that we don't want to give them our time.
So the automation, I don't think is the answer necessarily.
Like, don't just say well have your AI chat bot
answer their emails.
It's like, well I actually wanna connect with my students.
I wanna have time for them
but I'm also so exhausted by all the ways that I've had
to adapt since COVID and before.
And let's face it, like this is probably the biggest change
to hit education in a very long time, right?
Probably in our lifetimes. And that's tiring.
And I know that there's a lot hype and a lot of excitement
and a lot of things that these tools can do.
But just also recognizing that it's an additional burden
that you're asking faculty and students to take on
and then being like, you know,
how can I support you in that?
Not just like, you have to do this. Right.
- And I think I'd like to piggyback on that.
Oh yeah, please. Absolutely.
Piggybacking on that from the coordination side of it,
and I've seen it both with the AI realm
and open educational resources,
but the whole time it's creating the space
but allowing for the curiosity
and not just the curiosity in the space
that the person is in.
So for example, if I have a faculty member who's curious
about how to detect AI illegal use
or in unethical use versus ethical use.
So some of us have been in some of these talks today
and yesterday that talk about some of the powers
that AI can bring to those who have learning challenges,
who are not able to understand the materials
for whatever the reason.
And that the work that some of these AI
backbone software apps
and everything else, suddenly I lost all my English words,
but yeah, I'll use 'em all.
It'll work, you know, it says the linguist by the way.
So to have to have an open sense of curiosity,
but also understand the frustration and the challenges
and the limited space that we all have.
The classified staff also have some of these same questions,
same concerned, and same curiosities.
So being able to create spaces that allow that,
but also accepting the fact
that this is a round that has been around for a long time.
This is not just when ChatGPT became live to public,
that when we're talking about language models,
including the current large language models,
we have had these around four decades.
And that people who are behind the scenes and working
and developing, these have been working on this
for a very long time.
There's no way to just instantly go, oh, okay,
in two seconds I can understand everything about this.
They're like, you can't, no one can.
So chunk it out, go back to principles
of universal design for learning.
Chunk out that information.
Carve out the little piece you wanna try and understand now
and that you in the time and space that you have.
And I think the more that we do that, the easier this gets
to open your mind to possibilities and critiques as well.
- It's interesting 'cause in the Unconference,
I did a five minute lightning talk
and it started with curiosity
and talking about possibilities.
So I am the administrator,
but I also like to say that
I don't think I'm a typical administrator.
So there's nothing that is happening from my office
that is saying, you must do anything.
So when I first began,
I actually didn't have any staff in emerging technology.
It was just me and frankly ChatGPT trying
to build business plans.
And so I went into the faculty senate.
We have four colleges I went into, no, I think
they allowed me in in all of them.
So I went in and I kept being asked, what's your vision?
And I said, I don't have a vision. I need to hear from you.
And it's truly been creating that culture of
I want to understand number one, where your curiosities are,
but where are the pain points?
Because I consider myself the advocate
for everyone, for faculty, you know, starting
with faculty, recognizing the, the classified folks as well
and frankly the administrators
who are coming last in terms of our support.
And it's really been about
what structures can we build so
that we can get that information.
Because just a survey doesn't do that, right?
It's about conversations.
And so just engaging with the faculty senate
that first month I was in there really gave me an idea of,
okay, how can I even think about proceeding?
And that's been the most important aspect,
is the listening piece of it.
And then responding and recognizing that things also shift.
Now I can't, I'm sure there are people who think
that my office or I am dictating something
because those are perceptions
that just come with the title.
But I'm really trying to shift that,
that culture and talk about, talk to other leaders
around about that as well.
Because one of, from our cultural perspective, you know,
that that ability to go and try and fail,
I know a number of institutions,
that's a challenging piece
and people are afraid to talk about the failures part.
And so I go out and I talk about my failure parts
and I talk about how I'm using ChatGPT
so they can see an executive using ChatGPT and how I use it.
So trying to model that, it's okay,
but here's the okay parts of how I do that.
So a lot of it is trying to both model, create space
for the conversation, respond,
but also admit when I get it wrong.
And that's the piece
that I think is really critical
from a leadership perspective.
- Can I just wanna jump on real quick,
'cause there was a great quote in one
of the panels yesterday that like,
how do we get folks on board with technology?
It's like, not carrot nor stick, but FOMO, right?
It's like, you know, to tap into that curiosity is like,
you know, there are cool things that you can try out.
And it's like, it's not about compliance
or you know, mandating,
but it's about how do you make it look fun
or exciting or worth learning about.
- I was just gonna, I could not, I agree
with everything that's been said
and I don't wanna take the time to repeat
what was just shared.
And I'm just gonna say that it's easy
to empathize with the feeling of overwhelm
that faculty are experiencing
because I'm experiencing, yeah, I mean it takes a lot
to do your job and also add this huge slice.
This, you know, you blink five minutes
and you have new technology and new tool and a new trend
and you have to stay on top of it
because you have to be able to speak about it intelligently.
And so, so coming at things from a, like you said,
from a place of curiosity and listening
and advocating, like one of the things I've done is
advocating to acquire resources to support the faculty so
that they get the tools so
that they can experiment with them.
Because it's hard to learn something like this without
actually playing with it.
And so it's work in progress. We're not perfect.
And there are things, bigger questions
that all institutions have to answer
regarding data safety and security.
And if you remember the conversation this morning
from Karen Howe and Dr. Safi from UCLA is that
how do we protect the students?
How do we raise the students to be active,
engaged citizens so that they are able to advocate
for themselves around
what should AI look like in the coming years?
So that is, to me, that is a huge piece
that that is a big piece.
- If I may follow up a bit from an administrator
perspective, there's a whole infrastructure piece,
and you reminded me about this.
There's a whole infrastructure piece when we're talking
about AI, particularly around data.
And so from that administrative perspective,
I also have institutional research within
my portfolio.
And I started, one of the first things I did was started
to advocate for the recognition that we needed
to start talking about data governance.
When I first walked in, the IT staff
and the research staff were working on developing
or implementing an enterprise database warehouse.
And that's where you bring all your data
together into one place.
And it's very complicated
and it's taking a very long time to get there.
But I also did not believe we had the infrastructure
in place to actually support it the way it needed
to be supported to make it happen.
And so, because I'm an executive
and sitting at the table, I was able to bring
that position forward.
It was the first position, well, I only had got two,
it was one of two
that I brought forward recognizing that
as we're moving forward with AI,
if we don't get our data in order, we're not going
to be able to do any of this work.
So big part, another big part of what I'm looking at is
that big picture and the small picture all at all at once
to make sure that we're ready when the institution is ready.
- I wanna add one more thing if I may.
I think the ultimately based on
the previous conversations coming to the conversation from
a place of trust as opposed to a place of us versus them,
the administrators versus faculty and having faith that
the faculty care
and they come to work to do a great job
with all these things.
And so coming at things from that space allows
for the openings to have sincere conversations
and doing the listening.
So you can, because you can't influence someone
unless you understand their position.
And so that is critical.
And also thinking about the equity piece, going back
to the data, like another component is, okay, I guess
during COVID we gave the students the Chromebooks
and hotspots and all that good stuff.
So now how are we gonna ensure that students
who come from disadvantaged backgrounds
and they can't pay for themselves for AI subscriptions,
how are we gonna support them?
'Cause all of a sudden the digital divide is getting
wider and wider.
So addressing that and thinking about that.
- And with that in mind, thank you very much.
A second guiding question is,
in what ways can AI help close
or widen these equity gaps in higher education?
And you touched on that. How are we dealing with this?
- I think we have to start thinking about how we, first,
obviously the faculty are gonna be the biggest piece.
The faculty build the curriculum, the faculty have
to get the professional development
and provide the education the administration has
to support them in that.
But then also I would say advocacy is a big piece, like
where I sit, I mean we have to be in touch
with the chancellor's office
and the legislator to impact them in terms
of allocating resources to assure that we are able
to support the students with access to the tools.
So that's one piece.
- The first thing that comes to mind is
being inclusively collaborative.
Not just, going back to what Kathy, what you said
about getting away from that us versus them concept.
Making sure you have enough people
and as many people as possible in that room
to get as many perspectives.
It's not just having faculty massive air quotes,
but how many different types of faculty, CTE versus
transfer, non-credit versus credit.
You know, you get as many people, as many voices in
that room making sure it's not just a token classified
member, but as many classified voices as possible.
Because they all do so many different things
and they really are closer
to the students than even the faculty are.
If you do not have your retention specialists,
your disability resources services,
your library learning center,
all of those folks,
if you do not have them in the room
and are not listening to them,
you really do not have
the student perspective, which leads to the third part.
Get student senate involved,
get the students in those conversations.
You need to hear from them.
They are the ones going through this.
When we were putting together district teaching
and learning, for example, we made sure that if we could,
we could get a student representative on there.
And when we couldn't, when I was chair, I was going
to the student senate for the district
and connecting to as many of
our three student senate as possible.
So I could hear from them directly.
When we were putting out that AI guidance piece,
we gave it out to the student senate to say,
what's your view of this?
Is this really gonna be help if we give this
to faculty, for example,
is this really gonna be helpful for them?
So in that planning piece, making sure you have as many
viewpoints as possible is, I think crucial.
- Yeah, that student perspective has been so important.
One of the first panels that we had was a student panel
recognizing that, I really wanted
to make sure the faculty were hearing from the students.
And early on AI conversations were not happening
in the classrooms.
Very few people had syllabi statements and talking,
or had conversations around AI.
So our first student panel, and we've had quite a few now.
Our first student panel, they talked about the inequities
with their student peers.
They're the ones who brought that up.
Secondarily, they also talked about how they used it.
And one of our ESL students talked about
how they were using it
to help them understand the assignments
and then help them in their writing and learning grammar
and things of that nature.
So they were describing how they were using it
in a ethical manner,
but really talking about the equity components
that were in there and how it was creating equity for her
having this tool to help her both understand and write.
And so we took that further in our second year
and we had student interns who not only were part
of our weekly planning,
but then had projects on their own to engage
with other students and putting together their own
student panels.
And now we're actually expanding that further this year
and looking to have our student interns
and student externs working
with the different colleges
and bringing other students together as we're starting
to do this work and starting to really think about workshops
for students because they are asking for that.
And of course our survey just went out this week is
to students as well.
And we've got, I think as many in the first day
as we had in our first year of the student survey.
So that student first voice is, if you're not doing that,
that would be your first action step,
is to really start engaging with the students.
Yeah.
- So to kind of directly address the question of
how AI might widen equity gaps,
'Cause I work in our equity office as well.
So I think that one of the things
that has really struck me,
and I hope that we always think about when we're considering
different forms of AI adoption is this phrase that one
of my instructional designers mentioned to me.
And I was like, oh my gosh, that's amazing.
It's the right to talk to a human.
Like we should have the right to talk to a human.
And, you know, I went to a great panel at ASCCC
with Michelle Kinski Brock,
where she recommended the book called The Last Human Job,
which really talks about how automation is kind
of eroding our ability to do connective labor,
which is our ability to connect with other human beings
on a human level.
And I think that,
and one of the arguments of the book is that
as AI adoption gets more widespread,
people who have privilege
and have means will be able to connect with other humans,
whereas those who don't have resources will connect
with more chat bots or you know,
like the digital concierge whatever,
because it seems to be more efficient
and oh, everyone will have access,
but what are the benefits of actually interacting
with a human, right?
So that's one of the ways that I think
if we're not in intentional
and not sort of mindful of the value
of actually communicating with people on a human level,
then we could widen equity gaps
because then those who can afford genuine human interaction,
those who can afford like small to go to a school
that has smaller class sizes
where they get individualized attention from a teacher are
gonna be at an advantage.
Especially when you read all of the like sort of
business insider and Forbes about
what are the skills that students are gonna need?
They're gonna know how to work in teams,
how to work in groups, how to collaborate,
and like all those like durable skills
of talking to other people.
Like how are they gonna get that if they have been,
you know, most of their interactions have become automated.
- Hi, thank you. Pass the mic. Pass the mic.
Alright, so one thing as you were talking,
I was thinking about how,
and especially in your role, Sarah, how teachers, faculty,
people who do have access, either through their schools,
can potentially use these tools to create other things
to help with equity, right?
I mean, how do we address that?
Sorry, my apologies. Pass it, sorry.
- Pass it to the left hand side. Sorry.
There's a number of ways
and I'm gonna tap into the open educational resource base
on this one because that's really
where we can do the most good, I think.
There are a number of ways that we can currently use AI
as well as some developing technologies that are coming out
that will further enhance this.
So number one is, let's start
with the instructional materials themselves.
It has always made me cringe when I have talked
to my faculty colleagues who say I have
to use the publisher material, I don't know how
to create anything.
And I look them dead in the eye
and say, you've never created a question in your life.
You've never created a handout in your life.
Oh well of course I have. What do you think that is?
That's an instructional material.
So being able to unlock that power,
whether it is getting over the hump of, I don't know how
to start, alright, let me use the search engine of choice.
And let's face it, most of our campuses are connected either
to Microsoft, Google, or both.
So we have enterprise level of Copilot or of Gemini
or some of us have purchased when we're able to,
we have purchased licenses to other things to be able
to say, I don't know how to start,
but here's my initial idea.
Using that AI as a thought partner to say,
where could this creativity go?
I have a colleague at Cañada who
literally two years ago when all
of this started looked at me and said
I would never use AI for anything.
And I'm like, really?
So I happen to know this person
and I happen to know, they use the same test banks over
and over and over and over and over and over and over again.
And I said, "Wouldn't you like to have new test questions?"
"Well, yeah, but I don't know how to start that."
"Let me introduce you to ChatGPT."
And that was just two years ago now.
Now this person is creating all sorts
of different question types tapping into,
literally tapping into the learning outcomes for the module,
for the course to be able to say, I don't know how to start,
but this is my idea.
You can take that with respect to anything and adapt it.
And when we go into the open educational resource realm,
being able to say, I like this textbook, this OER textbook,
but it reflects a perspective that is not as appropriate
to my local students.
Some of my business faculty really love a couple
of textbooks for some of their biz courses
that come out of Canada.
Great finding, Nady,
but how's that gonna apply to San Mateo County or California
or heck even the US as a whole.
So being able to say, okay, I like this text
but I wanna modify it.
And for somebody like me, I'm a trained technical writer
and editor, I can pretty much do that.
I'm not gonna say in my sleep that's a little ambitious,
and I like my sleep,
but I can definitely do that fairly easily.
But if you do not a writing background, how do you start,
how do you start to modify that text
and do it in a way that not just benefits my students.
What about if I asked my students to use some of
these large language models, some of these creative apps,
to have them tell their own stories with respect
to the instructional materials to be able to say, okay,
that's the textbook edition and this is a really good model,
but how does it apply to my life, to my community
and my identities, plural, by the way, that's the power
that some of these tools can give us
to be able to unlock it.
Where we combine that
and then we combine that with digital literacy
and ethics and how to do this appropriately to admit
how you're using these tools,
the ways in which you're using these tools,
and how they have helped you to create on your own as well.
I think that's, and that's just starting
- And everything you just described is the same thing we
have to do with and for our students
because that's all about the AI literacy aspects.
So really finding opportunities
where our students can be engaged
in those same conversations.
I think I mentioned that we're going to be implementing
a student AI microcredential.
You know, we haven't really quite figured out
how it's going to roll out.
'Cause we can make it accessible.
That doesn't mean the student's going to use it.
We've talked about maybe we put it into
a personal growth class
and talk to a couple of personal growth faculty
and say, oh yeah, I'd be really excited about that.
This is a micro-credential
that San Diego state first created.
They're on their second year working with it
and they're talking about that, they're actually putting it
in their first year experience.
So how do we create opportunities for our students to learn
that that may not be directly in the classroom,
although we'd love our faculty, you know,
to do some of that as well.
What are all the different opportunities?
And it may be student to student opportunities,
whether it's a club, whether it's it's a workshop
that the student is running
for the student with our support.
We need to make sure we're getting that out there
for them as well.
From an equity perspective,
- I wanna carry this thought
and share how I think about approaching all of AI
and actually approaching how we should think about
our students and organizations.
And when I look at the student experience
and the research, we here repeatedly,
students, we need to provide more engaged learning.
The students, the business community tells us the students
are not coming with enough interpersonal
and communication and problem-solving skills.
There's the whole threat
of like integrity that the faculty feel pressure is like,
am I giving a student a grade that is not an honest grade
and passing them without them being truly have learned
and prepared for the labor force.
There is the post COVID isolation
that the students are experiencing and disconnect
and especially with them being so attached to their devices
and so on.
And so I am thinking that
there's one overarching strategy
that look different things in different contexts,
but it all links together.
And the overarching strategy is community building,
whether it is the two faculty talking to each other
and teaching each other,
the students engaging each other,
the faculty to the student.
Because even in an online class, if you have check-ins,
you will know your student.
And we all know the research tells us that
when you know someone, you are less likely
to engage in deceptive behavior with them
because there is like the human connection, right?
And the internships
to address the interpersonal communications
and engaged learning and so on.
And so building the community in different aspects in
different places where you take for example,
problem-based learning.
I don't know how many people have learned about
the Worcestershire institute.
I think somewhere back east, one of the major institutions
where they take a community problem
and you form a group of a learning community
to address the community problem using data
and collaborating to problem solve.
So having a community approach to any
of the, you know, whatever it is we're deciding on,
will be very powerful in addressing
the multitude of challenges we are facing.
People will get connected, they develop,
they know that they care.
Like for example, when students are choosing a major,
they still rely on their families
and family associates to decide on a major,
"Oh, my friend, their kid did this
and now they're making a good amount of money.
You think you should go research it?"
What's that? It's community, right?
And so even though we have all the technology we have,
the students are still based in their families,
in their communities, in the people around them,
in the high schools mentoring and so on and so forth.
So that's my thought on it.
- Yeah. Thank you.
So yeah, building on the sense of community,
if I may transition to our third guiding question
and last, based on your roles,
your different roles across your districts,
how are you leading to maintain the human element,
that connection, that community as AI continues
to proliferate higher ed?
- Me the last one.
So I didn't, I mean it was all in
my head then I thought I was talking.
Well, I will say I wanna give a huge shout out
to Learning Lab, California Education Learning Lab
because last year I was one of the AI faculty innovators
and residents and one of the things I did was leading
a statewide inner segmental interdisciplinary
AI learning community.
So it spanned California Community Colleges, CSUs, UCs,
and like, you know, with what Kathy was saying,
like it is about community building.
And I do think, you know, it's also valuable
to have it be interdisciplinary, inter segmental.
'Cause you know, as I know Fabi Torres,
who's also in the audience has mentioned like,
we need to be in these conversations
because the stuff that we're doing at the community college
level is in a lot of ways constrained
by what's allowed at the Cal States
and the UCs where our students are gonna go, you know,
if that's the path that they choose.
So that was like, just again,
like really diving into this idea of
how do we build community across different institutions,
across different regions of California.
Because here in Silicon Valley where De Anza is,
we have access to a lot of stuff that folks in like Humboldt
or you know, the Central Valley, like don't have.
And so having those conversations around like
what is it like, what are the conditions like
at your institution, in your different disciplines, like
what does that mean?
And it informs the way the work that we do.
But I also wanna say that, what else? Human element.
Oh gosh, I don't know.
I mean honestly, I mean like I feel like,
I know I might have sound like more pessimistic
and skeptic, you know, of the folks on the panel,
but I actually do teach a lot with AI in my classes.
I have students use it, I have them do,
I teach literature courses as well.
And I will just say I love when they stop thinking about
things like ChatGPT as the thing
that gives them the answer
and more as like, how do I like play around with it,
have fun with it, critique it, then the human element
of them comes out.
And if you've heard me talk before, you might've heard me
share this example,
but I teach a literature course where I invite students
to iterate with any LLM, a lot of them use ChatGPT,
and I say just have it create, I teach myth and folklore.
And so I said ask it to create a folk tale about aliens
that come from outer space
and are appalled by the ways that humans treat animals.
And I say keep iterating with it
until you are satisfied with the output.
So it's not just like copy and paste the first thing,
but it's like really interrogate, like
what did it give you and what do you like about it?
What do you not like about it?
And then they write a reflection about their process.
So I had one student who he did it
and he said, oh well, you know,
the first iteration I was like, oh, this sounds like really,
I don't know, it just sounds canned.
And it kind of reminded him of the movie predator.
And so he's like, now write it in the style
of the movie "Predator".
And so he wrote it and you know,
and the chat bot wrote it and he's like,
you know, I still don't like it.
It sounds like I don't like the dialogue.
It sounds really generic.
So they said, now write all of the dialogue
as Arnold Schwarzenegger movie quotes, right?
And so that was the next iteration.
And so then, and so hearing, seeing their process,
and then he even noticed, he said, oh, I noticed
that every iteration the story resolves
with him talking it out.
And he's like, that's boring, you know,
it's an English class, but you know, talking it out
to solve your problems was boring.
So he says, I want it to end in a dance battle.
And so then he has his final story
that it's a all Arnold Schwarzenegger get to the chopper
and then they, you know, like,
and then it ends in a dance battle.
That's what resolves.
And to me, like that's how I love seeing the human
in my students, how I love to see like,
what are you doing with this tool?
Like, have at it, have fun, and tell me what you think
and what you didn't like and how can we make it better?
So that's another way.
- Go ahead.
- So I don't know if I am,
you know, I can't say that this is what I am doing
or we are doing at EAVC now,
but I feel that we should be doing more of it.
And it is helping the students connect to themselves
through thinking and reflecting on their experiences.
Because I feel that a key,
like our, ultimately our goal is
to help the students be persistent, be successful, right?
We're all after that. And they have many barriers.
One of them is what do I do with this? How do I use it?
Is it okay? Is it not okay? And so on and so forth.
And I feel that an, again,
overarching strategy is
to help them find their life purpose.
Because through reflection
and connecting to themselves, then they have the reason,
the why for whatever it is that they're doing.
If this is the major, if this is the class, if this is
the internship surviving, waking up at five o'clock
in the morning to go take an early class
so you can end early and go get a job or do an internship.
This is how, like the real life of the students
or do a couple of jobs.
And so having that connection to themselves,
who they are, where they came from,
what is their family narrative, what's their history,
and having a purpose that's connected
and based in that will carry them to also to use AI
as a tool as opposed to being overtaken by AI.
So, I did a presentation I am gonna share
on this topic to students at Cal Poly Pomona in July,
150 students attended.
The SurveyMonkey did not work.
And so we ended up handing, I had post-it notes,
a bunch of post-it notes.
I was hungry to hear from the students what they thought
of the presentation.
Eighty out of the 150 present gave feedback.
And 60 out of the 80 gave the presentation
a score of 10 out of 10 that told me
that the student wanna talk about that.
Who am I? What am I trying to do? What is my role?
Where do I fit? What's my purpose?
What's my life plan? It's not just a class or a tool.
It's part of a bigger picture of who you are
and what you're about and what you are becoming.
And so that is the big, to me,
that's the bigger conversation.
- I'm recognizing we're getting towards our time
and I know we wanted to leave some questions,
so I'm gonna be very brief,
and you mentioned something,
I took one quote from this morning from Karen Howe
and it was, "AI needs to serve us.
We are not serving AI."
- Yep.
- And I think that's really important to remember also that,
you know, AI is something that can help build your capacity,
not take it away.
And that's really how I think about it
and how I try to talk about it.
Sometimes I don't wanna use the term tool with it
and I struggle between using it and not using it,
but just really thinking about
how it could help you in your capacity.
I think I started out, I mentioned that I didn't have
any staff when I started, any team when I started.
And that's, I use ChatGPT to ideate with
because that's what I had at the moment.
So how how do we use it to build our own capacity,
not necessarily that it's going to do things for us,
but help us think about how we're doing things.
So I'm gonna leave it at that.
- And I'm gonna pick up on that
with a quote from somebody else who talked yesterday.
So Christopher Lafayette, who was in the AI companion panel,
one of the key takeaways, he hit I think at least three
or four times in a couple different ways,
and I'm gonna paraphrase it as well, is to say,
basically understand that what we are really good at
is empathy, connection, collaboration,
that human element.
AI doesn't do that very well.
What AI can do are the things that very well are some
of the things that we don't do very well.
So the very quick in intake of information
and quick analysis, so that in my roles, plural,
continues to be that realm of understand that,
yes, AI can help us do a number of different things,
but it also is incumbent upon us to continue to humanize
how we interact with all aspects of technology, not just AI.
So when I come across the person,
not just faculty member, there's plenty of classified
and administrators who also,
and students even who are absolutely anti-AI.
And when you allow them to see that it is through some
of these AI based adaptive technologies
that we have students who actually can unlock education,
they can go through that door
and be part of the education sphere,
when we are able to take these amazing ideas
that as educators, no matter what our positions are,
we have these amazing ideas through decades in most cases
of training and education and instruction.
And we can take those ideas and share them with people
in ways that they can understand,
even though we ourselves may not be very good writers in our
own estimations, by the way,
most folks are actually pretty good writers, right, Chesa.
And you just don't want to admit it,
or don't understand the power of that you have.
AI can help us do that,
but we have to bring that human element to it.
When we do, we suddenly do have a really great connection.
And I've always thought of this era of AI as kind of like,
sorry, I'm a secret Trekky.
So if you, you know, fellow Trekkies,
or even if you've seen one episode
or one movie of "Star Trek", you know the ship's computer,
ship's computer can do a lot of things,
but it's the human element that made "Star Trek"
and that the, I shouldn't say humans,
the anthropomorphic type folks
and the AI, the ship's computer together
we're the problem solvers.
When you combine the two pieces, it's really powerful.
- Thank you.
And we do have one last question,
which is considering the humanity
and what you talked about in community,
and there's sometimes like a slightly dark side
to that is what about the AI shaming, what about people
who maybe use AI but are afraid to admit it?
Because people, I'll admit that, right?
Being a woman of color, English is not my first language.
That some of us are a little bit more susceptible
to issues like that.
How would you address that in
as we're building this community?
Thank you.
- I can start off with this one really quickly.
I learned from a colleague of mine many years ago
who was an ESL professor at Cañada.
When she starts off her class,
it doesn't matter if we're talking level one
to the very most basic level, all the way to level four,
if a student starts to apologize for not being able
to express themselves in English, she says,
stop apologizing, you're still learning.
And that is what I would say.
That is what I do say to folks who feel shameful
for some reason for using some of these technologies.
You should feel shame if you're using them unethically,
that's a whole other question.
But if you're using them to help you do something,
to express yourself, to connect with others, stop it.
You're still learning how to use it. Stop apologizing.
- And just to add on that, I've noticed, I teach English,
and a lot of students who are ashamed to admit
that they use it, it's because they're ashamed to admit
that they don't think their English is good enough.
- Yes, yes. - And I feel like
that is the deeper sort of question
or like place that I wanna be curious about
because I think a lot, and then when I ask them it is
that like, well, English is not my first language
and so I just don't think I'm good enough.
And this goes back to, you know, the topic of trust
that was brought up earlier, which is that
one of the dangers of these technologies is that folks
who lack a sort of innate sense of trusting themselves,
that they have value, that their opinions matter,
and that their voice, however,
like grammatically incorrect it is,
is still valuable, are gonna be more susceptible
to relying on the tools
that end up making them sound like everybody else.
And so we have to understand the motivation that some people
are so afraid of their own voice
that they would much rather sound like,
you know, the generic ChatGPT voice than like themselves.
And I feel like for me as an educator, that's the place
where I see like, that's where I wanna intervene.
Not did you cheat? 'Cause I don't care.
Like, I just wanna know why,
like why did you not rely on your own innate knowledge
or your your own ability to ask questions
and your own curiosity to like have
that conversation with me?
- I'm gonna say that being in a leadership position,
you set the tone for the conversations in meetings
in how you interact.
And people are not stupid.
They pick up on cues
and they know when you treat people with respect and dignity
and when you don't.
And if you truly, genuinely treat people with respect
and dignity, you give them the grace
of not knowing.
And also you carry yourself in a way
where you're, you know, presenting your authentic,
authentic self with the things you do know
and the things you don't know,
and therefore you're more comfortable to ask questions
because like, hey, I mean, I share my story, for example,
I started in ESL classes and at Mount Sac
and I couldn't put a sentence of English.
And so I have published articles and I have my PhD
and so I was afraid initially
to share my story and, you know,
because oversharing like TMI, they tell me, my kids used
to tell me TMI.
But the truth is, if we are authentic
and we we share who we are genuinely,
then we are more likely to make people comfortable saying
where they're at and what they're afraid of
and how they're feeling about things
and how them move to the next step.
And having that tone when you're in a leadership position
is so critical.
And people know it.
People feel it and they know it. Thank you.
- I'll just add to it, that being
as a leader, being vulnerable.
And really we had an AI day
and I shared that I created the opening speech
with the help of AI.
And that was shocking to some people.
Now, it was my own words that I put in there.
Like it, I didn't ask it to create an opening speech.
I had all these thoughts that I wanted,
but I also wanted them to be organized so
that people could understand them well.
And so even I, yes, I might be able to sit down
and write something that's really understandable,
but I also know that if I'm going to do it and do it quickly
and I want specific things in it, this is one way
that I can build my capacity.
And so I talk about how I do that.
One of my emails was brought up in a training session at
another college and it was brought up
from a negative perspective.
Look, Vice Chancellor Fischthal did this.
And I'm like, okay, that's okay. I'm okay with that.
Yes, there were parts of it that I did.
It was to describe the AI Challenge Grant
and I wanted to pull out the details using, so I did.
So it's being out there vulnerable
and saying, yes, I too am doing this.
- That is our time. Thank you so very much.
Let's give it up for our panelists. Woo.
- Thank you. - Thank you.
Appreciate you all.
Questions come on up.